RG 069:005, Leila M. Church Collection
Connecticut State Library
Leila M. Church collection
1901-1932
Connecticut State Library
Church, Leila M., 1879-1932
7.25 cubic feet
Leila M. Church (1879-1932) was a writer, composer and director of plays and historical pageants primarily in Connecticut. The collection includes scripts, stories, essays, personal papers, scores and correspondence in reference to her professional artistic work.
RG069_005
T001320
Biographical Note
Leila M. Church of Rockville, Connecticut, was a writer and director of plays and historical pageants. She lived in Rockville from her birth in August 1879 to her death on August 7, 1932 at the age of 53. She became well known in Connecticut and New England primarily for her historical pageants.
Miss Church began her literary career by writing short stories that she sent to multiple editors in New York City. She studied piano at the Hartford Conservatory of Music from 1902-1903. She used her knowledge of music to incorporate original and published musical scores within her pageants and plays. By 1918 she was writing, composing, and directing pageants and plays. She also took charge for much of the scenic and costuming decisions. Her services were requested throughout New England until the year of her death in 1932.
Scope and Content
The collection is arranged into 12 series: Outlines, scripts and manuscripts, One act plays, Programs, Sheet music and composition, Stories, Personal papers, Correspondence, Press releases, Newspaper clippings, Speeches, Photographs, and Sewing patterns.
Series 1. Outlines, Scripts, and Manuscripts, 1901-1931, contains first drafts of outlines, manuscripts and final drafts of script for plays and pageants, directorial notes on specific pageants as well as backstage notes on costumes or scenery.
Series 2. One Act Plays, undated, consists of the scripts for five one act plays.
Series 3. Programs,1918-1930, contains the programs from pageants and plays written and directed by Leila M. Church, comprising of towns throughout the state of Connecticut as well as other New England states.
Series 4. Sheet Music and Composition, 1928-1932, consists of original work written by Miss Church as well as professional work used in pageants or plays, as well as full orchestra arrangements.
Series 5. Stories, circa 1904-1905, contains short stories, published and unpublished that were sent to editors in New York City.
Series 6. Personal Papers, 1902-1931, consists of a diary of her music lessons, essays, personal notes, as well as her mother's poetry books.
Series 7. Correspondence, 1903-1917, consists of professional correspondence in reference to publishing short stories written during the early stages of her career.
Series 8. Press Releases, 1927-1931, consists of an ad about Miss Church's pageant services, as well as reviews on pageants.
Series 9. Newspaper Clippings, 1906-1927, contains clippings in reference to specific pageants as well as the published story in Youth's Companion from September 1909.
Series 10. Speeches, undated, contains a speech written for J. Mahoney to address Columbus Day.
Series 11. Photographs, 1920-1931, contains professional photographs of pageants. Participants from different towns in costume posing as well as cast photos.
Series 12. Sewing Patterns, undated, consists of a pattern to sew an 1840-1860s style boy's coat.
Arrangement
Arranged into 12 series.
Series 1. Outlines, Scripts, and Manuscripts, 1901-1931, arranged alphabetically.
Series 2. One Act Plays, undated, arranged alphabetically by title.
Series 3. Programs, 1918-1930, arranged alphabetically by state and then town.
Series 4. Sheet Music and Composition, 1928-1932, arranged alphabetically.
Series 5. Stories, circa 1904-1905, arranged alphabetically by title.
Series 6. Personal Papers, 1902-1931, arranged alphabetically.
Series 7. Correspondence, 1903-1917, arranged alphabetically by sender.
Series 8. Press Releases, 1927-1931, arranged alphabetically.
Series 9. Newspaper Clippings, 1906-1927, arranged alphabetically.
Series 10. Speeches, undated.
Series 11, Photographs, 1920-1931, arranged alphabetically by town of pageant.
Series 12, Sewing Patterns, undated.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Pageants -- Connecticut; Historical drama, American -- Connecticut; American literature -- Connecticut -- Women Authors; United States -- History, Local
Places:
Hartford (Conn.); Rockville (Conn.); Willimantic (Conn.); Manchester (Conn.); Connecticut; New York (City); New England
Persons:
Church, Leila M., 1879-1932
Document Types:
Staged photographs; Commercial correspondence; Correspondence; Scripts (documents); Sheet music; Plays (document genre); Scores; Templates (shaping tools); Theater programs; Diaries
Restrictions on Access
The sewing pattern is stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
Original papers from Series 1. Outlines, Scripts and Manuscripts, Series 4. Sheet Music and Composition, and Series 9. Newspaper Clippings that have been removed and noted in the container list are restricted due to their fragile condition. Use copies of the removed papers are located in Series 1. Outlines Scripts and Manuscripts, Series 4. Sheet Music and Composition, and Series 9 Newspaper Clippings where noted in the container list.
See the policy.
Provenance
Part of the collection was received on June 21, 1934, from Miss Marietta Fitch of Rockville, Connecticut. The bulk and remainder of the collection was received from Mr. Leon Woodward, former Town Clerk of Willington, Connecticut, on March 26, 1956.
Container List
- Series 1. Outlines, Scripts, and Manuscripts, 1901-1931
  - Aetna Pageant, undated; 1 manuscript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Antrim historical notes and lines, undated; 5 outlines (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antrim participants, 1927 August 12; 1 outline (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Cat and The King" / "Puss In Boots" properties list, undated; 1 outline (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Cat and The King" / "Puss In Boots", undated; 18 scripts (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Columbia, Connecticut Pageant, undated; 1 manuscript (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Community Chest Pageant, undated; 1 manuscript (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Dancing Thro The Ages", undated; 1 script (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Easter and Christmas pageants, undated; 9 manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Economy", undated; 7 scripts (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - "The Enchanted...", undated; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "River Song", Enfield, Connecticut pageant, undated; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Fancyland", undated; 3 scripts (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - "Fandangle", undated; 1 script (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Glastonbury, Connecticut Pageant, 1924; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Glastonbury, Connecticut Pageant, 1925; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 200th Anniversary Buckingham Church Pageant, Glastonbury, Connecticut, 1931 May 15; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Glastonbury, Connecticut Pageant, undated; 3 choruses (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Glastonbury Pageant, undated; 4 verses (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Grange notes and verses, undated; 8 verses (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Beautiful Story" Grange Pageant, 1901 August 11; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Grange Pageant, Storrs, Connecticut, 1931 August 11; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Grange Pageant, Willimantic, Connecticut, 1932 May 28; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hartford, Connecticut Pageant, undated; 3 outlines (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Aetna Pageant, Hartford, Connecticut, 1928; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Community Chest Play, Hartford, Connecticut, 1928; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fire Pageant, Hartford, Connecticut, 1925 June; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fire Pageant "Echo", Hartford, Connecticut, 1927; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hartford historical notes, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Romance of Other Days", Presbyterian Church, Hartford, Connecticut, undated; 8 manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Hartford, Connecticut Y.W.C.A., undated; 1 manuscript (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "The House That Jacob Built", undated; 2 outlines (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "The Jade Doll" verses, undated; 2 verses (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "The Jade Doll" and song, undated; 1 script (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "The Jade Doll", undated; 19 scripts (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - "Lincoln", 1929; 1 manuscript (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Little Women" tableaus, undated; 1 outline (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "The Magic Carpet", undated; 10 scripts (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manchester, Connecticut Pageant notes, undated; 1 manuscript (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Manchester, Connecticut, 1923; 4 manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Manchester, Connecticut Pageant costumes and notes, circa 1923 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "The Mulberry Tree", 1926 February; 1 manuscript (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "The Mulberry Tree", undated; 5 scripts (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Nathan Hale Pageant, undated; 1 manuscript (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Nathan Hale Pageant, "The Advancing Glory", 1926; 1 manuscript (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - New London Pageant notes and choruses, undated; 5 outlines (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New London Pageant, undated; 2 manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "O Colonial Matchmaker", 1931 March 12; 1 manuscript (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Pageant...", undated; 1 manuscript (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "The Plant", undated; 1 manuscript (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Radio program, undated; 5 manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Railroad Station Play", undated; 19 scripts (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - George Washington Pageant, "Rice Flowers For The President", undated; 1 manuscript (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Armistice Day Pageant, Rockville, Connecticut, circa 1927; 3 outlines (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Armistice Day Pageant, Rockville, Connecticut, 1927; 1 manuscript (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Armistice Day Pageant, Rockville, Connecticut, 1928; 1 manuscript (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Simple Simon" / "Midsummer Nights Dream", undated; 5 scripts (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Someday Silas", Vernon, Connecticut, 1931 July 3; 1 manuscript (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Southington, Connecticut Church Anniversary Pageant, 1924; 1 manuscript (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Uncle and Mary scene, undated; 1 manuscript (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Hiawatha", Wethersfield, Connecticut, undated; 2 manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Wallingford, Connecticut Pageant, 1920; 5 manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "What Makes A Man", undated; 5 outlines (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Acts one and two..., undated; 1 outline (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Backstage paperwork, undated; 1 outline (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Springfield, Massachusetts Pageant, undated; 1 outline (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated; 1 outline (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous outlines of pageants, undated; 5 outlines (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Manuscripts, 1927 June; 2 manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Manuscripts, 1929; 2 manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Additional lines and manuscripts, undated; 21 manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - Readings and scenes, undated; 16 manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Verses, undated; 13 manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
  - Tableau arrangements, circa 1930; 5 outlines (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series 2. One Act Plays, undated
  - "A Colonial Wedding", undated; 2 dupilicate copies (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "In A Quaker Garden", undated; 5 duplicate copies (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Just Peggy", undated; 2 duplicate copies (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "The Little Seamstress" / "Nellie's Dilemma", undated; 3 duplicate copies (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "Where's Bobby?", undated; 6 duplicate copies (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series 3. Programs, 1918-1930
  - "Pageant of The Nations", Danielson, Connecticut, 1920 February 17 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "The Jade Doll", East Hartford, Connecticut, 1923 February 19-21 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Pageant of The Nations", East Hartford, Connecticut, 1918 September 26-27 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Passing Through", East Hartford, Connecticut, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Glastonbury, Connecticut historical pageant, 1924 September-1925 September (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Pageant and Garden Party", Girls' Club of the Two Hartfords, Hartford, Connecticut, 1925 June 30 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "The Magic Carpet", Manchester, Connecticut, 1920 February 2-3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "The Mulberry Tree", Manchester, Connecticut, 1926 April 21 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Puss In Boots", Manchester, Connecticut, 1924 January 23 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Armistice Day Pageant, Rockville, Connecticut, 1927 November 11-1928 November 12 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "The Cat and The King", Southington, Connecticut:, 1927 January 25 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "The Jade Doll", Southington, Connecticut, 1925 February 3-4 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "Pageant of The Nations", Southington, Connecticut, November 21 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 200th Anniversary First Congregational Church Pageant, Southington, Connecticut, 1924 May 23-25 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "Pageant of The Nations", Suffield, Connecticut, 1919 November 6-7 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "The Magic Carpet", Wallingford, Connecticut, 1921 June 1-2 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "The Magic Carpet", Wallingford, Connecticut, 1921 November 4 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - "The Jade Doll", Windsor, Connecticut, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - "The Magic Carpet", Windsor, Connecticut, 1922 February 24-25 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - "The Magic Carpet", Willimantic, Connecticut, 1922 November 9-10 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "The Jade Doll", Connecticut, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - "The Magic Carpet", East Weymouth, Massachusetts, 1925 April 28 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - "Celebration of the 250th Anniversary of the Town of Northfield, Massachusetts, June, 1673-1923", 1923 June 22-24 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - "Puss In Boots", North Weymouth, Massachusetts, February 23-24 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Knights of History", Springfield, Massachusetts, 1923 February 2-5 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Greenfield Military Band, Massachusetts, 1929 October 30-31 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Antrim, New Hampshire, 1927 August 12-14 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - "The Jade Doll", Concord, New Hampshire, 1930 December 16-17 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - New London, New Hampshire, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Winchester, New Hampshire, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 30)
- Series 4. Sheet Music and Composition, 1928-1932
  - "Cast Chorus", undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "Coming Thru The Rye", undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Drink To Me", undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "Dundee Hymn", undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Grieg Sonata", undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "In A Rose Garden", undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Indian Love Song", undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "The Jade Doll", undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Jade Doll Song", undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Lass With A Delicate Air", undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - "Last Night With The Nightingale", undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Loose Sheet Music, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Manchester, Connecticut, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - "March of The Men...", undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous bass tunes, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - "A Mighty Fortress", undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - "Neekimo's Song", undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - "Neapolitan Boat Song", undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - "Oh West Thou In The Could Blast", undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "The Pigeon Suite", undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - "Scots Wha' Hae", undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - "Soldiers Joy", undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - "What Makes A Man", 1932 February 22 (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
  - Antrim pageant, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Band arrangements: multiple songs, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Band music: Manchester, Northfield, and Wallingford, Connecticut, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Blue Skies": Armistice Pageant, 1928 November 12 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Hiawatha's Wedding Feast", undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Indian Chant", undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Indian Love Song" arrangements, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Loose music named, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "The Magic Carpet", undated (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Manuscript music for Cosmopolitian, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous orchestra Arrangements, undated (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - Miscellaneous piano, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous piano music, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous published work used in pageants, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - "My Love She's But A Lassie Yet", undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Pageant, New London, Connecticut, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "Passing Through", undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "Puss In Boots", undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Songs used in pageants, undated (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
- Series 5. Stories, circa 1904-1905
  - "A Childs Desire", undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "A Colonial Cinderella", undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Convincing P.A.", undated; 2 duplicate copies (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "The Crowning of The Day", undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "The Day of Fulfilment", undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Don", undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "Dora", undated; 2 duplicate copies (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "Her Brother's Sister", undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "Her Day of Rebellion", undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "A Matter of Phonetics", undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "Miss Hannah's Sarah", undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "The Passing Away of Amanda", undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "The Perambulations of Snyder von Bukelwitz", undated; 2 duplicate copies (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Published, circa 1904-1905 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - "The Quest of Emil", undated; 2 duplicate copies (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - "The Refractoriness of Lucy", undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - "Taking Posession", undated; 3 duplicate copies (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "A Tale of Three Chairs", undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - "An Unsuccessful Elopement", undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - "The Vows of Yesterday", undated; 2 duplicate copies (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - "The Wheel of Fate", undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Series 6. Personal Papers, 1902-1931
  - Connecticut Historical Society, 1931 May 28 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Diary of music lessons, circa 1902-1903 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Diary of music lessons extract, undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - "The Custard Pie", undated; 3 readings (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - "Youth Is Like A Fountain", 1925; 2 essays (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - In Memory of Henry Appleby, undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Jennie Church book of poetry, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Jennie Church poetry, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Life and Character of Henry Muggleshine, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Series 7. Correspondence, 1903-1917
  - Film companies, 1917 February 27-March 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1904-1909 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Sedgewick, Ellerly, 1903-1907 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series 8. Press Releases, 1927-1931
  - Ad, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes, circa 1927-1931 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Plainville, Connecticut Operetta, 1927 May (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series 9. Newspaper Clippings, 1906-1927
  - Fire Pageant "Echo", Hartford, Connecticut, 1927 June 29 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Manchester, Connecticut, 1923 October 5-7 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Armistice, Rockville, Connecticut, 1927 November 11 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Wallingford, Connecticut, 1920 September 4-5 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Illustrated London News, 1906 February 24 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Youth's Companion, 1909 September 30 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Series 10. Speeches, undated
  - Columbus Day for J. Mahoney, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Series 11. Photographs, 1920-1931
  - French Group, Manchester, Connecticut, 1920 February 2-3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 200th anniversary Buckingham Church Pageant, Glastonbury, Connecticut, 1931 May 15 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Festival, Litchfield, Connecticut, undated (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
  - "Pageant of the Nations", undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Russian Group, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Pageant, Wethersfield, Connecticut, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous pageant photographs, undated; 6 photographs (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
  - Miscellaneous group pageant, undated; 2 photographs (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Series 12. Sewing Patterns, undated
  - Boys coat, 1840-1860, undated (Box Oversize Drawer)
- Restricted, 1923, undated
  - "Hiawatha", Wethersfield, Connecticut, undated; 2 manuscripts (Box 15, Folder 1)
    For a use copy of the restricted manuscript see Series 1. Outlines, Scripts, and Manuscripts.
  - "Oh West In Thou Could Blast", undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    For a use copy of the restricted sheet music see Series 4. Sheet Music and Composition.
  - Manchester, Connecticut, 1923 October 6 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    For a use copy of the restricted newspaper see Series 9. Newspaper Clippings.